A Guide to the Personal Papers of Roye Lowry, 1958-1985
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Personal Papers of Roye Lowry, 1958-1985
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 108
6 boxes.
Lowry, Roye L.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Roye Lowry in 2002.
Biographical Information
Roye Lowry was an active member of the Arlington community for decades, serving in various positions of local government and participating in numerous capacities of volunteer work. Lowry came to Arlington in 1957 after serving in the foreign service and in 1961 was elected to the Arlington County Board, where he served for a single term. He ran under the nonpartisan Arlingtonians for a Better County (ABC) slate and served as Board Chairman for a year in 1964. He was also Chairman and member on the Civic Federation's Revenue and Expenditures Committee and its Schools Committee. In 1965, Lowry was defeated in the county board race by Republican Kenneth M. Haggerty.
Additionally, Lowry served as a PTA member and officer at the then-Glencarlyn Elementary School (now Campbell Elementary School), Kenmore Middle School, and Wakefield High School. Among his other civic appointments were: President of the Metropolitan Council of Governments; Chairman of the Executive Committee of the Metropolitan Council of Governments; Treasurer of the Northern Virginia Transportation Commission; and Chairman of the Arlington County Industrial Development Authority. Additionally, he held positions in the Forest Glen Civic Association beginning in 1961 and was one of its delegates to the Arlington County Civic Federation. These included: Chairman of the Special Committee on Housing, Chairman of the Housing Committee, and member of the Executive Committee; representative to the School Board Budget Advisory Council and a citizen member of the school system's Social Studies Advisory Committee.
Scope and Content
RG 108 measures 2.5 linear feet and spans the years 1958 to 1985. Most of the materials are concentrated in the years surrounding Lowry's time campaign for office and his time in office, from 1961-1965. This collection contains materials from Roye Lowry's personal documents relating to his time in public office, his campaigns for public office, as well as general materials relating to the governance and development of Arlington.
Included in the collection are a variety of materials related to the campaigns and elections of various county officials. Additionally, there are materials related to Lowry's own campaigns and election to the County Board. Having run as a candidate for Arlingtonians for a Better County (ABC), there is a focus on candidates who ran with that organization.
A bulk of the working materials are related to Lowry's involvement with the Arlington Civic Federation Housing Committee and the Arlington School Board. Series 6, Publications, largely focuses on development and planning. Many were published by Arlington County, both on a countywide scale and in individual departments and committees. Also included is a thesis draft written by a student at Michigan State University that focuses on the role of the ABC in partisan politics. Finally, Series 9, Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, is composed of newspaper clippings collected by Lowry, the bulk of which were put together in a scrapbook by Lowry. These articles are on a range of topics related to Arlington during Lowry's time in government. Most of the articles are complete, but many were not designated with a publication source or date, and some clippings are incomplete fragments of the original articles.
Arrangement
Record Group 108 is arranged into series thematically. Within the series, materials are organized chronologically. Titles in quotation marks ("") indicate that the materials in these folders were originally filed together by Lowry and have been kept in their original order and labeled as they were originally labeled. There are some oversized materials in this collection, which have been moved to appropriate housing. Separation sheets have been added to denote their original placement.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
An oral history interview was conducted with Roye Lowry in 2007 as part of the "Smart Growth Documentary" project documenting the development of the Metro system. Its call number is VA 974.4295 A7243oh ser. 8. No. 10.
An oral history was conducted by the Library with Dr. Kenneth Haggerty, who defeated Roye Lowry in the County Board election in 1965. Recorded in 1985, it details Haggerty's time in office and its call number is VA 975.5295 A7243oh ser.3 no.52.
The records of Arlingtonians for a Better County (ABC) are housed in RG 94, and contain information on the organization from 1948-1992, including significant overlap with Roye Lowry's time in office.
Photos of Roye Lowry can be found in PG 100, Arlington County Photographs, 1898-1997. A published version of the Michigan State study conducted by Franklin Felt, "A Study of a Nonpartisan Political Organization: The Arlingtonians for a Better County (ABC)," can be found at the Center for Local History with call number 363.975 F325s. A preliminary draft of the study is included in this collection in file 4 of Series 6, Publications.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia -- Politics and government; Lowry, Roye L.; Arlington County (Va.); Arlington (Va.)
Contents List
- Campaign and Elections Materials
  - External Campaign Materials
    - 1960 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - Leo Urbanske, " 1966 campaign" (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
  - Roye Lowry Personal Campaign Materials
    - Roye Lowry campaign, 1961 (1 of 2) (Box 1)
    - Roye Lowry campaign, 1961 (2 of 2) (Box 1)
    - Roye Lowry campaign, 1965 (Box 1)
  - General Arlington Elections Materials
    - "Precinct voting," 1961-1971 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Board vote tallies, 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Elections, 1969 (Box 1)
- Roye Lowry County Board-Relate Materials
  - "Miscellaneous," 1958-1966 (Box 1)
  - Roye Lowry campaign County Board Materials, 1961-1966 (Box 2)
  - "County Board appearances," 1963-1967 (Box 2)
  - "County Manager," 1963-1968 (Box 2)
  - "Citizen complaints," 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Second National Conference on Highways and Urban Development, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Roye Lowry speech to ABC, 1965 (Box 2)
  - "Articles of interest" (Box 2)
  - Roye Lowry, personal notes (Box 2)
  - Roye Lowry, personal material on redevelopment in Arlington (Box 2)
  - Roye Lowry, personal material on housing in Arlington (Box 2)
- Arlington Civic Federation Housing Committee Materials
  - "Civic Federation Housing Committee," 1964-1968 (Box 2)
  - "Arlington Civic Federation Housing Committee," 1966-1972 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
  - "Arlington Civic Federation Housing Committee," 1966-1972 (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - "Arlington Civic Federation Housing Committee - Apartment Committee of Planning Commission," 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - "Executive Committee, Arlington County Civic Federation," 1970-1973 (Box 3)
  - Arlington County Civic Federation, miscellaneous, 1973-1980 (Box 3)
- Race and Discrimination in Arlington
  - Materials related to race and discrimination, 1963 (Box 3)
- Arlington County School Board
  - Arlington County School Board materials, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - "School Board meetings," 1964-1974 (Box 3)
  - Report: Advisory Committee for Defining School Attendance Areas, 1965 (Box 3)
  - "School Improvement Committee," 1968-1973 (Box 3)
  - League of Women Voters: Financing Arlington Public Schools, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Arlington Public Schools Tentative Budget, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
- Publications
  - Arlington County 10-Year Financial Projection, 1959 (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Financial Report, FY 1959-1960 (Box 4)
  - Arlington County 10-Year Financial Projection, 1960 (Box 4)
  - A Study of Nonpartisan Political Organization: The Arlingtonians for a Better County, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Master Plan, 1961 (Box 4)
  - General Land Use Plan, 1961-1964 (Box 4)
  - General Land Use Plan, 1961-1966 (Box 4)
  - General Land Use Plan, 1961-1975 (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Annual Report, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Potomac Nature Trails, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Data Processing in Arlington, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Office of Planning - Apartment Development by census tract, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Office of Planning - Population and Housing by census tract, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Neighborhood Conservation programs, 1965-1976 (1 of 2) (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Neighborhood Conservation programs, 1965-1976 (2 of 2) (Box 4)
  - Proposed Physical Development Policies for Washington, D.C. 1965-1985 (Box 4)
  - Regional Development Guide, 1966-2000 (Box 4)
  - A Report for Citizens, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County Annual Report, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County 2-year budget projection, 1966/67, 1967/68 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County Office of Planning report - Rosslyn, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Report of the Arlington County Board Advisory Committee on Health and Welfare, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Arlington Office Buildings, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Report: Police Advisory Committee to the Arlington County Board, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Report for the Arlington County Board: The Arlington Arts Center, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Arlington Citizen's Report: 1968, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Jefferson Davis Corridor Five-Year Plan, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Report to the Citizens, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Jefferson Davis Corridor Five-Year Plan, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Park and Open Space Inventory, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Water related land use planning guidelines, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Report to the Citizens, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Arlington Trends, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Virginia Polytechnic newsletter, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Arlington's Critical Choices: A long-range county improvement program, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Recommended General Land Use Plan, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Ballston: A Community Plan, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County Capital Improvement Program, 1978-1982 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County Capital Improvement Program, 1980-1985 (Box 6)
  - Fiscal 1981 Proposed Budget Volume 1: Activity Summaries (Box 6)
- State Codes
  - Code of Virginia, housing (amended in 1960) (Box 6)
  - Virginia State Codes, 1972 (Box 6)
- Roye Lowry General Working Materials
  - Arlington park development, 1960-1973 (Box 6)
  - Briefing on "poverty areas," 1966 (Box 6)
  - Report, Committee on Health and Welfare, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Remarks by Harold J. Castro, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Garden Apartment Committee report, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Environmental Quality Committee report, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Materials related to construction of Cultural Center, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Arlington Committee of 100 meetings, 1974, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Report from the Economic Development Commission, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Report of Revenues and Expenditures Committee, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Glencarlyn Conservation report (Box 6)
  - "Zoning Cases Inconsistent With Land Use Plan" (Box 6)
- Newspaper and Magazine Clippings
  - "Scrapbook" (Box 6)
  - "1961 pre-campaign general information" (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings (Box 6)
  - Washington World, November-December 1964 (Box 6)